"Do GLP-1 Drugs Like Ozempic (Semaglutide)
Cause Pancreatitis and Pancreatic Cancer?"
The most common
adverse side effects
of Ozempic-type
weight-loss drugs
are gastrointestinal issues,
including nausea, vomiting,
diarrhea, and constipation,
which I talked about
in a previous video,
as well as excessive
lean muscle loss
and gallbladder issues,
discussed
in a subsequent video,
but Ozempic may also heighten
the risk of pancreatitis,
kidney failure,
and thyroid cancer.
I talked about the thyroid
cancer risk in my last video.
Many of the kidney issues
may stem from dehydration
due to excessive vomiting
or diarrhea
caused by the drugs,
but what
about the pancreas inflammation?
Analyzing
the prescription records
of 16 million Americans,
compared to taking
an older class
of weight-loss drugs,
the use of GLP-1 drugs
like Ozempic
was associated with nine times
more pancreatitis,
as well as four times
higher risk
of bowel obstruction.
Remember, GLP-1 slows down
your digestive tract.
That’s part of the reason
people get nauseous and barfy,
but that’s also part of why
you feel fuller for longer
and lose weight.
But sometimes, it can
make your gut so sluggish,
it stops working,
and you get a blockage
that could become
a surgical emergency.
It’s super rare, though.
The number needed to harm
after one year of use is 1,223,
meaning that
more than 1,000 people
would have to take the drug
for a year
to cause a single extra case
of bowel obstruction.
So, even after 10 years
of treatment,
your cumulative risk
would be less than one percent.
But what about this 800 percent
increased risk of pancreatitis?
Digestive hormones like GLP-1
act on multiple targets
within the body,
with multiple effects,
perhaps more "magic shotgun"
than "magic bullet,"
but maybe not so magical
for the pancreas.
GLP-1 receptors are
expressed abundantly
throughout the pancreas,
and in response
to GLP-1 therapy,
the cells of the pancreas
proliferate,
swelling the organ
and potentially
squeezing off ducts,
causing inflammation,
at least in rats,
but that led to human studies
like this,
suggesting that GLP-1 drugs
may increase the odds
of pancreatitis
as much as six-fold.
This led some investigators
to conclude
that the balance of evidence
suggests an association
between the use
of GLP-1 based therapies
and acute pancreatitis.
The major concern
is not pancreatitis, though.
Acute pancreatitis is
unpleasant enough,
but the major concern is
subclinical, asymptomatic
inflammation of the pancreas,
because inflammation
of the pancreas
is well known to predispose
to pancreatic cancer,
which is one of the deadliest
forms of cancer.
And some of the rats did show
potentially premalignant changes
in their pancreases
on these drugs.
The concern is that
the pro-proliferative actions
of GLP-1 could take
premalignant lesions
and accelerate their progression
towards cancer.
Remember how these drugs
were modeled off a compound
found in Gila monster saliva?
Few have paused to wonder why
they would produce it.
The answer is that
the Gila monster
is a desert lizard that goes
for weeks or even months
between meals
and conserves energy
during those intervals
by shrinking
its digestive tract,
including its pancreas.
So, when it finally does eat,
it needs a way
to rapidly proliferate
its tissues.
After reviewing thousands
of pages of documents
obtained through
freedom of information requests,
a British Medical Journal
investigation
unearthed unpublished data
from animal and human studies
that point to pathological
changes in the pancreas,
including attempts
by drug companies
to suppress scientific debate
by withholding
important safety data
from the public.
Why have the companies been
so slow to respond
to this threat?
Because of
the "three monkey paradigm,"
which operates as follows.
Companies are
legally responsible
for monitoring the safety
of their own products,
but obviously can’t be
held responsible
for tackling a safety concern
that does not exist.
A concern that can be
plausibly doubted or denied
carries no legal liability,
whereas one that gives rise
to serious consideration
leaves the door wide open
to lawsuits.
Thus, inviting companies
to monitor the safety
of their own products
provides them
with the strongest
possible incentive
for failing to do so,
an instance of the law
of unintended consequences.
The three monkeys,
who neither hear
nor see nor speak,
have been allowed to flourish
at the heart of our system
for protecting the public.
"After careful reflection,"
wrote a professor of medicine
at the Mayo Clinic,
"most patients and clinicians
may opt to avoid
GLP-1 based drugs
or at least avoid using them
for a prolonged
period of time."
And this was all before
this pivotal study came out,
where researchers obtained
transplant-quality pancreases
from, like, accident victims
who had been taking GLP-1 drugs
for at least a year
before they died,
and every single pancreas
showed abnormalities,
marked enlargement, dysplasia,
and even a few little tumors.
This was all discovered
more than a decade ago, though.
Where are we now?
It remains unclear
whether the use of GLP-1 drugs
is linked to an increased risk
of pancreatic cancer.
But trials
would have to be enormous
to exclude an increased risk,
and unless the rules
change radically
by the time
they are to be reported,
most of the data
will remain hidden
from independent scrutiny.
And as one Johns Hopkins
drug safety researcher asked,
"The fundamental question is
who bears the burden
of the passage of time
while these debates
are settled?"
Thousands
of pancreatic cancer cases
have been reportedly tied
to GLP-1 drugs, like Ozempic,
based on the U.S. Food
and Drug Administration’s
Adverse Events Reporting System,
but adverse event databases
that rely on voluntary reporting
are limited by the potential
for reporting bias.
That’s like the Centers
for Disease Control’s
VAERS database,
the Vaccine Adverse Events
Reporting System.
During COVID,
the more states were inclined
to vote Republican,
the more likely their vaccine
recipients or clinicians
were to report
COVID vaccine side effects;
so, maybe there was some kind
of similar reporting bias
among those who submit
their pancreatic cancer
to the FDA?
Either way, if there is
even a remote chance
that certain drugs
can have an impact
on cancer development
and progression,
then such risks
should not be taken lightly.
But if you really don’t want
to get cancer,
then you really don’t want
to be overweight.
Based on a study
following millions of people,
the longer you’re overweight
or obese,
the higher your apparent risk
of 18 different kinds of cancer.
So, even if you cared
only about cancer,
might these drugs actually lower
your overall cancer risk
if they caused
enough weight loss?
A meta-analysis
of bariatric surgery studies
found that those
going under the knife
tend to lose so much weight
that they have
a significantly lower risk
of getting cancer
and appear to cut
their risk of dying from cancer
nearly in half.
This modeling study suggests
that widespread usage
of these new-generation
weight-loss drugs, like Ozempic,
could prevent more than,
like, 1 out of 100 cancers
over the next 25 years.
And that’s just cancer.
Wouldn’t just
the cardiovascular benefits
of losing a lot of weight alone
outweigh any potential risks?
That’s the subject
of my next video:
Do the benefits
outweigh the risks?